<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The plain man's essay for England's prosperity more particularly referred and submitted to the consideration of the Lords and Commons in Parliament assembled, 1698.</title>
            <author>Philalethes.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54980</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2364</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10783</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13114245</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13114245</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97731</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54980)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97731)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 749:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The plain man's essay for England's prosperity more particularly referred and submitted to the consideration of the Lords and Commons in Parliament assembled, 1698.</title>
                  <author>Philalethes.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Signed: Philalethes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97731:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97731:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Plain Man's Eſſay</hi> FOR ENGLAND'S Proſperity: More particularly REFERRED and SUBMITTED To the Conſideration of the LORDS and COMMONS In Parliament Aſſembled, 1698.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>A. Baldwin,</hi> near the
<hi>Oxford Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> MDCXCVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97731:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97731:2"/>
            <head>THE Plain Man's Eſſay FOR <hi>England</hi>'s Proſperity,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Advantages of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> are of ſo Univerſal Influence and Concern, that ſince every one in their reſpective Spheres muſt bear a part in both relations, it will ſcarce be denied, but they may, nay ought to act one alſo, according to their ſeveral Powers and Capacities.</p>
            <p>This may Apologize for my thus caſting a Mite into <hi>the Publick Treaſury:</hi> And while I but offer at preſerving Your Honours in the diſtinguiſhing Characters and Conſideration Your Anceſtors and Predeceſſors have been eminent for, and deſervedly enjoyed beyond Us of a Lower and inferior Rank, I preſume to promiſe my ſelf, That my Attempt will not be held inconſiſtent with that branch of duty to our Neighbour,
<hi>The ordering my ſelf lowly and reverently to all my Betters,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as we are taught in our Church Catechiſm.</p>
            <p>For though the Advantages are many and great which we have ſenſibly recovered by means of the late Happy Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, yet the Nation was too long a dividing and corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:97731:3"/> and too far ſunk with narrow, miſtaken Notions of <hi>Chriſtian and Civil Liberty,</hi> to be at once freed from all Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and reſtor'd to that extenſive Charity, which
<hi>beareth</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 7.</note> 
               <hi>all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This makes me hope, and willing to perſuade my ſelf, That though mens Notions and Actings have ſeem'd in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſpects very oppoſite, and too too paſſionate and exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating, that this however hath proceeded from a <hi>miſtaken</hi> firſt, and then a <hi>miſguided Zeal,</hi> rather than from any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Malice of one towards another, or ill-will at bottom to their <hi>Native Country:</hi> For when our common Danger was grown to that heighth as became ſenſible and apparent to them, we have ſeen men of the moſt ſuſpected Pretenſions ſtrike in, and cloſe with, under God, the happy Inſtrument of our Deliverance, Our preſent Gracious King, in his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Expedition for <hi>Preſerving of the Proteſtant Religion, and for</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. of O's Declarat.</note> 
               <hi>Reſtoring the Laws and Liberties of</hi> England, Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland.</p>
            <p>But though I apprehend we may eaſily err, and ſo judge amiſs, in imputing over-much to mens Wills, and too little to our Sins and Miſdoings, the grievous Preſſures the Nation was reduced to, and which further threatned it; yet it's every one's duty to prevent, what in him lies, the pernicious <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Practices</hi> that brought both <hi>Church and State</hi> to ſuch Extremities, and which may again obſtruct their Settlement; <hi>ſo that there may be no more danger of the Nation's falling at any</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>time hereafter under Arbitrary Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as <hi>the watchman woketh but in vain, except the Lord doth keep</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 127.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>the city;</hi> ſo altogether in vain is it to preſume and expect that human Means ſhould proſper for our preſervation, if we continue by our Sins to work our own deſtruction.</p>
            <p>There are ſo many excellent Diſcourſes full fraught with ſuch cogent Reaſons continually almoſt both preached and publiſhed, ſhewing the indiſpenſible neceſſity of a good Life, and withal of a Reformation of Manners in the Age we live, that I ſhall not pretend to inſiſt on that part; and indeed I think it altogether needleſs, here eſpecially: For I do not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that this bears any part in our Modern Controverſies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97731:3"/> nor do I meet with any body that contradicts it in particular: For which Reaſons I chuſe rather to hint one Occaſion (among many others, it's not improbable) whence it comes, that a matter ſo obvious in it ſelf, ſo univerſally acknowledg'd, ſo ſtrenuouſly enforced, and in its own nature and conſequence ſo beneficial to Mankind, takes ſo little place, That nothing in Religion ſeems near ſo like a
<hi>contradiction,</hi> as men are to themſelves.</p>
            <p>I am partly aware, that in this licentious Age, rather than of perfect Freedom, the common cry goes ſo much of a rank Infidelity and groſs Atheiſm, that ſome will be ready to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt mens Lives are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not ſuch a <hi>contradiction</hi> to their Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as I here inſinuate: But under favour, and in the words of a Reverend and Learned Prelate of our Church, <hi>A</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi>'s Paſtoral Care. Lord <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi>'s Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſays.</note> 
               <hi>Learned</hi> or Contemplative <hi>Atheiſm is ſo hard a thing to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that unleſs a man's powers are firſt ſtrangely vitiated, it is not eaſy to ſee how any one can bring himſelf to it;</hi> and therefore 'tis that God is obſerved (as the Great Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> remarks) <hi>never to have wrought a Miracle to convince Atheiſm, becauſe his Ordinary Works convince it.</hi> But the truth ſeems rather to lie here (as the ſame excellent Perſon further expreſſeth it);<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>That all that impugn a Received Religion or Superſtition, are by the Adverſe Party branded with the Name of Atheiſts;</hi> ſo I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, it likewiſe noted, by a Modern Author, That
<q>in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> an Atheiſt once ſignified a Perſon that medled with the Pope's Mitre, or the Monks fat Bellies; and thus nearer home in ſome paſt times;</q> It was little better to queſtion <hi>the Divine Right</hi> of a ſpecial Form of Eccleſiaſtical, or Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, <hi>excluſive of all others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are indeed but too too many, who in a profligate way take, it may be, a ſort of fantaſtical vain pride in talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after an Atheiſtical manner, as well as in living ſo too, which is what I with others deny not, but bewail; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I look not on this, as I ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to proceed from a form'd and ſetled Judgment, but as a prejudice they have imbib'd from men only; I will now give ſome account whence I take both the one and the other in great part to ariſe and prevail ſo far.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97731:4"/>Though no Human Authority in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Religious Matters is deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and abſolutely binding among men, no not where
<hi>Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility</hi> is pretended; much leſs with ſuch who renounce a Claim ſo empty, but withal ſo artificial, yet in fact I incline to think, it will be owned that nothing ſways ſo much as the Authority and Example of Profeſſors, eſpecially Superiors of all ſorts (it matters not to diſtinguiſh here, any more than to inſtance particulars) and that men for the moſt part, even in the weightieſt Concerns of this World, and another, judge more from what they ſee and hear, than what they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand; and conſequently form and regulate their Speech and Actions more by
<hi>Senſe,</hi> than true <hi>Knowledge:</hi> Which made that Great and Good Man, the late Archbiſhop <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> ſay, <hi>That</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fifth Vol. of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, p. 118.</note> 
               <hi>he could not ſee how Chriſtianity can ever gain much ground in the world, till it be better adorned and recommended by the Profeſſors of it.</hi> Nor is it eaſy to conceive, how in this ſtate of Nature it can be otherwiſe, ſince God in his wiſdom hath conſtituted the make and frame of Mankind ſuch, <hi>That Speculative Arguments do not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of
<hi>Sarum</hi>'s Paſtoral Care.</note> 
               <hi>reach the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of the greateſt part, who are only capable of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ones;</hi> whence it's the leſs to be wondred at, if ſo many (conſidering beſides we are ſo continually beſet with outward Temptations, and inbred Paſſions) take up with plauſible <hi>Colours,</hi> rather than <hi>juſt Cauſes</hi> of
<hi>Atheiſm and Immorality,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Le Clerc</hi> of Incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity.</note> who <hi>cannot go back to the very Spring, and examine the Chriſtian Religion in it ſelf, and ſuch as it is in the Writings of the Apoſtles:</hi> And from hence it ſeems naturally to follow, That moſt Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples falſe Notions and evil Practices ſpring from <hi>Prejudices</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up among men, without any real Sentiments of their own: And if this be ſo, we may well reckon our ſelves ſo much our <hi>Brothers keepers,</hi> that it imports us more than a little to beware, in our reſpective ſtations, how through our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults we ſcandalize our Neighbour, leſt, while we ſeverally in our turns admoniſh one another, our ſelves become
<hi>Caſtaways,</hi> and withal draw our Brethren into the like
<hi>condemnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This more eſpecially imports the <hi>Clergy,</hi> as the peculiar<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am</hi> of Confuſ. and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vol. of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Ambaſſadors of God, and as <hi>they, who deriving neither from Prince nor People, but from Jeſus Chriſt, as the Immediate Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of his Myſteries, interpoſe with greater aſſurance than any of another Robe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97731:4"/>Then the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> as who by their great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of Birth and Education, have not only ſtronger and more particular inducements, and who cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out clearer Light for the promoting our Sovereign Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor's Glory, and our Neighbours Good; no more than they can be without great influences on thoſe of <hi>low Degree:</hi> And how generally is it even demanded in the common Affairs and Faſhions of life, to be honoured and imitated by Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors; and how ready and obſequious, for the moſt part, are theſe to mimick thoſe above them; but, as the Nature of Man is prone to ill, in the worſt things more eſpecially? And herein is one circumſtance ſo peculiar, and ſo proper to Men of the firſt Quality, that it gives great aſſurance of their being touch'd therewith; for ſince they appear upon all occaſions ſo piqu'd in Honour, to be outdone in what they take to and affect; that few things continue longer a Mode, or very va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable, but until others take in with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> them; I humbly move them to reſolve themſelves, What Vice or Immorality it is, in which the very meaneſt among us, in their way, are not capable (I dare not ſay of excelling, but) of exceeding even the Higheſt and the Greateſt? Which alone, methinks, is ſufficient to make men truly and throughly affected with the Principles of Honour and Diſtinction (which their Blood and Degree naturally enough inſpire) head and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a juſt and neceſſary Reformation of Manners, ſince the very ſcum of the People are ſo univerſally infected with all ſorts of Vice and Immorality, and I wiſh it was not to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (as before intimated) from the Contagion of the
<hi>Higheſt:</hi> But Corruption, and ſo too Reformation, of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, deſcends as naturally as Love is ſaid to do: How neceſſary then and commendable is ſuch a <hi>Revolution</hi> as this? And how would it work and prove a mighty <hi>Deliverance</hi> indeed to us and our Poſterities? And without it, ſuffer me to ſay, The being hitherto ſpared (while the very Heavens have conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued lowring as of late for ſome time paſt; tho our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours at preſent ſeem to feel the more immediate and preſſing effects of unkindly Seaſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuffer me however to ſay, That this or any ſuch like Forbearance of God towards us) is ſo far from ſecuring a Bleſſing in the End<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the Mercies
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97731:5"/> which the Almighty's Long-ſuffering and Forbearance hath hitherto extended to us, will one day (if a timely Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Amendment do not follow) become our moſt certain, juſt, and terrible
<hi>Confuſion:</hi> This we cannot but know, as we all acknowledge by our
<hi>publick Profeſſion of Religion, and a Form at leaſt of Godlineſs and Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip:</hi> But what availeth it to confeſs God with our Lips, if by our Lives we deny him? Or with what face can we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect God's Bleſſing on us and our Endeavours; unleſs we are found doing <hi>his Work,</hi> which is moſt properly <hi>our own</hi> too?</p>
            <p>Not that we may however take up our Reſt here, as if no more was required or neceſſary, than the abſtaining from evil, or at moſt, the gaining in our ſelves a holy diſpoſition and temper of mind; or that both our Religious and Civil Duties were not more <hi>Poſitive</hi> than
<hi>Negative,</hi> more <hi>Active</hi> than <hi>Paſſive:</hi> No, the former is but a juſt and due preparation for the latter; for there are ſins of <hi>Omiſſion</hi> no leſs than of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion;</hi> and we may, and I fear often do, tempt and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke <hi>Providence</hi> as well by neglecting as by abuſing it. Leſt therefore we incur God Almighty's diſpleaſure through our own default, we muſt not ſtop ſhort here: And becauſe <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals are for the moſt part uncertain, and oftentimes fallaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> I will now with humble deference and ſubmiſſion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to hint at ſome few particulars, which to me ſeem to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the
<hi>Eſſence</hi> of every well Conſtituted Society, whether we conſider it in a <hi>Religious</hi> or <hi>Civil</hi> Capacity.</p>
            <p>I obſerve it then in the firſt place, as, in my poor appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, <hi>a capitol Error,</hi> and which ſeems to hold ſome pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel in Church and State, that whereas Chriſt's Church ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends<note place="margin">Rom. 10. 13.</note> it ſelf <hi>to all that call on his name;</hi> and that all ought to be embraced upon the plain and direct Terms of the Goſpel, <hi>whom coming to him, himſelf will in no wiſe caſt out:</hi> And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,<note place="margin">John 6. 37.</note> in like manner, all Mankind ought to conſider themſelves as ſo many Members, making up one great entire Body throughout the Univerſe, to whoſe happineſs and welfare all the divided and ſubdivided Societies, Parties and Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Men ſhould be ſubſervient, and eſteem their own
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97731:5"/> private ſeparate Good as therein included: it is but too often ſeen, that in all particular Societies, whether for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious or Civil purpoſes, Men conſider themſelves and their ſmall ſeparate Parties as the whole, rather than as parts; and ſo cauſe Schiſms and Factions in Church and State, by taking upon them more than of right belongs apart; and through each Party's pretending to uſurp, and that all others ſhould obſerve and obey them <hi>disjunctly;</hi> inſtead of their co-opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting reciprocally according to their Stations, Ranks and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, to the reſpective good and edification of the more entire Body of that Society, and inſtead of ſuch Societies acting (as much as may be) for the common univerſal bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and advantage of <hi>Mankind collectively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's eaſily ſeen whither this in a great meaſure tends; and there hath ſo very much ill accrued, and withal ſo little good, to the ſeveral diſtinguiſhing and contending Parties within our ſelves in their ſeveral turns, and according to the various Scenes of publick Affairs: And particularly we have lately had (under the weight of Taxes, the misfortunes of War, and more eſpecially the notorious impairing the Coin of the Nation; and all this, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> too in a young Government, and ſcarce throughly ſetled) ſuch ſenſible and immediate effects of the
<hi>Toleration</hi> hitherto allowed, that it's the more amazing to ſee any People ſo blinded, at leaſt, towards their Country's and the publick Intereſt, as to think the permiſſion that is, too much; whereas
<hi>Religion,</hi> as well as <hi>Policy,</hi> inclines rather to<note place="margin">Lord <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi>'s Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſays.</note> extend it further: For as it is noted, <hi>Chriſt's Coat indeed had no ſeam, but the Church's Veſture was of divers colours; whereupon it's ſaid,</hi> In veſte varietas ſit, ſciſſura non ſit; <hi>They be two things, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity:</hi> Then as to Policy, What greater ſecurity, under God, can there be to any regular, well-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Government, than the making all People eaſy, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in their higheſt and moſt tender concern of this World and another; and that it be their ſpecial Intereſt to maintain it, and then withal <hi>to teach men ſo?</hi> Thus all men (as is equal in Nature, and ſo alſo under Government) are, according to their reſpective Demerits, let in to run the hazards, bear the burthens, and ſhare in common the Profits and Honours of the Government they live under, as well as enjoy its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97731:6"/> Protection together with the reſt of their
<hi>Brethren,</hi> who are all ſuch by the Bonds of <hi>Nature,</hi> of
<hi>Religion,</hi> and of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another ill conſequence of mens narrow Notions and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Conſideration for themſelves; beſides their muttering at <hi>Liberty of Conſcience (the great and ſpecial Bleſſing of Heaven, as well as of this Reign)</hi> is the grumbling ſome diſcover at <hi>the Liberty of the Preſs,</hi> which hath been, and is ſo peculiarly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental for the diſpelling <hi>Popiſh Ignorance,</hi> and all ſuch <hi>blind and paſſive Superſtitions,</hi> that the <hi>Reformation</hi> it ſelf had prov'd <hi>Abortive,</hi> had not God of his mercy brought to light the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Art of Printing; whereby we are mutually enabled to reap the Advantages of one another's Labours: And there can be nothing of a civil nature aſſign'd ſo much the cauſe why that hath hitherto made no greater progreſs, but ſeems rather in many places at this day to loſe ground, than <hi>Perſecution,</hi> and <hi>the Reſtraint of the Preſs.</hi> Papiſts indeed may be ſaid to be ſo far in the right, as to take right Meaſures for the upholding their <hi>Temporal Hierarchy, or Spiritual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation;</hi> but it's unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable why <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> with a Cauſe that needs only a true Liberty and Light to render it amiable and prevailing over the face of the whole Earth, and to bring in in God's appointed time <hi>the fulneſs of the Gentiles,</hi> ſhould tread in their ſteps and paths of Darkneſs, which is their chief, I may ſay their only, Subter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge; or that we ſhould turn <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> upon our ſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, God be thanked, it's not yet in their power to ſet any over us.</p>
            <p>There are againſt this (as againſt what not?) ſome Objections may be ſtarted, but they appear either ſuch Cavils, or
<hi>Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices,</hi> or at moſt affect only ſome wild Exceſſes of Licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, not a <hi>Juſt Liberty,</hi> and which may be well enough and eaſily regulated, without denying or deſtroying ſuch <hi>a Liberty of mens publiſhing their Thoughts to the World,</hi> that I here purpoſely paſs them by in ſilence, as of no weight to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the matter, nor altogether conſiſtent with my propoſed brevity; only, leſt it ſeem to thwart what I have contended for but even now, <hi>the Reform of Manners,</hi> I crave leave to add, That there need no <hi>Superviſors of the Preſs</hi> to prevent the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of Principles or Notions, in themſelves <hi>Scandalous,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97731:6"/> Immoral or Prophane,</hi> becauſe it was ſcarce ever, or rather never known, that under the <hi>Inquiſition of the Preſs,</hi> any have ſought an <hi>Imprimatur</hi> for them.</p>
            <p>A ſecond fatal Error, and of ſomewhat like kind with the former, I take to be the Opinion ſome ſeem to entertain of the
<hi>Perfection of our Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Reformation and State-ſettlement;</hi> for as ſoon as they become ſo poſſeſs'd, they no longer ſtrive after any thing beyond themſelves and their preſent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: And the nature of Man, and of all human things beſides, is ſuch, that if they grow not, nor improve, be their height and degree of Perfection, Settlement, or Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment what it will, they ſtand not long at a ſtay, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, degenerate, and grow worſe and worſe; <hi>non progredi eſt regredi:</hi> But the <hi>Reformation</hi> was never look'd upon, nor can be underſtood to be or to have been, <hi>compleat.</hi> The firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers were eminent indeed to a degree, but the Evil had been too long contracting, and was grown to too great a Head, to have its <hi>Reform</hi> be the Work but of a Day, of a Reign, or even of an Age. That Reverend and Learned Prelate of our Church, who hath ſo inconteſtably Reform'd and Imbeliſh'd its Hiſtory, will ſcarce be rejected as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competent Judge or Witneſs in this Caſe; and he hath not long ſince aſſur'd the World, That <hi>there remains yet a great deal to be done for the compleating of our Reformation.</hi> But the Account he gives of its having made <hi>a full ſtand for above an hundred years,</hi> would not, 'tis like, be ſo properly inſerted here, as it is in the Preface to his <hi>Diſcourſe of the Paſtoral Care.</hi> But put the Caſe, <hi>That thoſe who ſucceeded our firſt moſt worthy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, had gone on, and taken the ſame liberty in examining theirs, as they did their Predeceſſors Opinions:</hi> And that thereby, as it could ſcarce have fail'd, they had happily diſcover'd much more Truth: If any ſay, That then the ſame would have continued to us and to Poſterity; by the very ſelf-ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may they ſay too, That no Errors or Corruptions have ever been ſince our Saviour Chriſt's and his Apoſtles times: And ſo farewell at once all <hi>Reformation,</hi> paſt, preſent, or to come. <hi>But I would only ask</hi> (in the Lord
<hi>Bacon</hi>'s words),<note place="margin">Reſuſcitat.</note> 
               <hi>why the Civil State ſhould be purged and reformed by good and wholeſome Laws, deviſing Remedies as faſt as time breedeth Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs?
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97731:7"/> And contrariwiſe, the Eccleſiaſtical State ſhould ſtill continue upon the Dregs of Time, and receive no Alteration. But if it be ſaid to me, That there is a difference between Civil Cauſes and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical; they may as well tell me, That Churches and Chappels need no Reparations, tho Caſtles and Houſes do. Whereas common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſpeak truth, Dilapidations of the Inward and Spiritual Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of the Church of God are in all times as great as the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and Material.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then as to the <hi>State-Settlement,</hi> let any body, without going further, but look into His Majeſty's <hi>moſt juſt and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Declarations,</hi> upon his ſo Charitable Expedition hither; and then, conſidering the many notorious Breaches on our Civil and Religious Rights therein expreſſed and implied, let him, I ſay, ſatisfy himſelf, if he can, that there is nothing more to do, notwithſtanding the great Advance towards the <hi>promoting a Settlement of the Religion, and of the Liberties and Properties of the Subjects, upon ſo ſure a Foundation, that there</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. of O's Addit. Declarat.</note> 
               <hi>may be no danger of the Nations relapſing into the like Miſeries at any time hereafter;</hi> which we are abundantly aſſured was his Majeſty's only deſign in that Undertaking.</p>
            <p>It would be no hard matter to ſuggeſt divers Particulars, that have a natural Tendency to compleat <hi>ſo Pious, ſo Glorious an Enterpriſe;</hi> and men are apt, with a good and laudable Intention, to inſtance in what occurs for that purpoſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their various Sentiments and Turns of Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; as, among others, in a <hi>General Naturalization,</hi> and <hi>a Publick Regiſtry, &amp;c.</hi> But I ſhall content my ſelf here to point at only in ſhort ſome few of the many Inſtances parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culariz'd in the forementioned Declarations, as carrying with them both their own <hi>Evidence</hi> and <hi>Authority;</hi> referring the reſt to the more accurate, able, and diſcerning Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of thoſe and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuch the <hi>Lords and Commons,</hi> as upon <hi>the Agreement and Concurrence of both Houſes, having entire Confidence, That his Highneſs the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>would perfect the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſo far advanced by him,</hi> &amp;c. did <hi>reſolve and declare the Prince and Princeſs of</hi> Orange, <hi>King and Queen of</hi> England, France,
<hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And did <hi>pray them to accept the Crown and Royal Dignity of the ſaid Kingdoms and Dominions accordingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97731:7"/>The Particulars then that I ſhall here on this Head touch upon, are in order as I find them there; where the 10th Paragraph runs thus, <hi>They have alſo invaded the Privileges, and ſeized on the Charters of moſt of thoſe Towns that have a Right to be repreſented by their Burgeſſes in Parliament; and have procured Surrenders to be made of them; by which the Magiſtrates in them have delivered up all their Rights and Privileges, to be diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of at the pleaſure of thoſe Evil Counſellors; who have thereupon placed new Magiſtrates in thoſe Towns, ſuch as they can moſt entirely confide in; and in many of them they have put Popiſh Magiſtrates, notwithſtanding the Incapacities under which the Law has put them.</hi> Again in the 18th Paragraph we have theſe words,
<hi>And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Charters and Privileges of thoſe Boroughs that have a Right to ſend Burgeſſes to Parliament, they have ordered ſuch Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to be made, as they thought fit and neceſſary for aſſuring themſelves of all the Members that are to be choſen by thoſe Corporations.</hi> And in the 21ſt it's declared, <hi>That in order to (the having a free and lawful Parliament aſſembled) all the late Charters, by which the Elections of Burgeſſes are limited, contrary to the ancient cuſtoms, ſhall be conſidered as null and of no force: And likewiſe all Magiſtrates who have been unjuſtly turned out, ſhall forthwith reſume their former Employments, as well as all the Boroughs of</hi> England,
<hi>ſhall return again to their ancient Preſcriptions and Charters.</hi> But whether the bare reſtoring theſe to their ancient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors and their Succeſſors, eſpecially after ſuch bold preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of manifeſt violations committed upon them, be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ſecurity againſt a <hi>precarious Tenure</hi> in times to come, I ſubmit to your better and more deliberate Conſiderations; and may it pleaſe your Honours to conſider withal, what His Majeſty, <hi>Prince-like,</hi> adds in his concurring ſecond Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>That the ſeeming releaſe from their great Oppreſſions offered to the City of</hi> London <hi>upon the hearing of his Preparations to aſſiſt the People, was done only, hoping thereby to quiet the People, and to divert them from demanding a ſecure Re-eſtabliſhment of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Laws:</hi> And that ſuch ſecurity might not in aftertimes prove fallacious, <hi>His Highneſs,</hi> out of his deep foreſight and Princely Wiſdom (<hi>whoſe care of the People hath been all along tranſcendent</hi>) at the ſame time ſubjoin'd,
<hi>That the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiveneſs of the redreſs was apparent, while they laid down no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97731:8"/> which they may not take up at pleaſure, and they reſerved en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and not ſo much as mentioned their claims and pretences to an Arbitrary and Deſpotick Power; which has been the Root of all their Oppreſſion, and of the total Subverſion of the Government: Hinc illae Lachrime.</hi> His <hi>Majeſty</hi> herein hath abundantly done his part; the preceding <hi>Parliaments</hi> have gone a good way, and 'tis not to be doubted, but <hi>Your Honours</hi> will proceed. And that <hi>the good people of England</hi> will perſevere and adhere to His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> his moſt Juſt and Gracious <hi>Declarations;</hi> as alſo to <hi>the preſent Government founded thereupon and thereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next particular in courſe that follows, and which alſo depends much on the preceding Article (as the foregoing References do plainly intimate) is the Being and Buſineſs of Parliaments, concerning which the
<hi>18th</hi> Paragraph uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulably aſſerts, That <hi>according to the Conſtitution of the Engliſh Government and immemorial Cuſtom, all Elections of Parliament-men ought to he made with an intire Liberty, without any ſort of force, or the requiring the Electors to chuſe ſuch perſons as ſhall be named to them: And the perſons thus freely Elected ought to give their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions freely upon all matters, that are brought before them, having the good of the Nation ever before their Eyes, and following in all things the Dictates of their Conſcience.</hi> This manifeſtly relates, as to the <hi>Freedom of Election</hi> of Members, ſo alſo to the <hi>entire freedom of ſuch Members acting afterwards:</hi> Towards the former of theſe eſpecially, there have been ſome good things Enacted; but yet the laying Penalties or Incapacities on <hi>Candidates</hi> may not probably be ſufficient (I ſay not to cure, but) to prevent the evil, without laying the
<hi>Electors</hi> themſelves under like Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Incapacities; nor is there good reaſon why the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſhould be interdicted, and not the latter. In caſe it be ſaid, That if no body did <hi>Tempt,</hi> no body would be <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted;</hi> I reply, if no body was to be, or would be
<hi>corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> no body would <hi>tempt;</hi> ſo that by this means there would, at leaſt, be both <hi>leſs Temptation and leſs Corruption.</hi> As to the other branch, their <hi>Freedom of acting,</hi> the name of the <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner Parliament</hi> is not ſo ſtale as to be forgotten, nor of the nature of ſowr Wines, which by turning Vinegar come again in vogue. God Almighty hath taught man, that to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97731:8"/> 
               <hi>delivered from evil,</hi> he muſt pray,
<hi>not to be led into temptation.</hi> There is a Reverend and Worthy Claſs among you, whoſe <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> lay ſome time ſince under the imputation of the <hi>dead Weight;</hi> which yet was not owing ſo much to men's averſion, or their objections to the Order it ſelf (however craftily it hath been given out and vulgarly taken) as to their <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pendencies,</hi> and the effects that theſe have wrought in times paſt; and if ever the like effects appear in the <hi>other Houſe,</hi> as the conſequence would not be leſs
<hi>fatal,</hi> ſo the <hi>Parties</hi> themſelves would not be leſs
<hi>obnoxious.</hi> It would be well therefore, if ſuch modeſt and reaſonable proviſions were herein timely made, as conſiſt with the publick ſervice; and that this <hi>Rock of Offence</hi> be ſo done away, as that our Enemies may not at any time whatever, have it, or take it, for a handle to pervert, blaſt, or invalidate <hi>any Parliaments Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt thing that I ſhall here mention of this nature is, That His <hi>Majeſty</hi> was ſo very cautious of endangering the Nation, though by a temporary or occaſional means of its preſervation, and of even giving umbrage of any ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, that after he had repreſented in a peculiar inſtance (§. 19.) the failure, or rather neglect, of the then Evil Counſellors, in <hi>not doing more to ſatisfy the many good Subjects of theſe Kingdoms, or to put an end to their doubts;</hi> He declares in very expreſs terms (§. 21.) that <hi>he brought over with him a force ſufficient, by the bleſſing of God, to defend him from the violence</hi> (only) <hi>of thoſe</hi> (the then) <hi>Evil Counſellors.</hi> And further
<hi>promiſeth (§. 23.) That as ſoon as the ſtate of the Nation will admit of it, he would ſend back all thoſe Foreign Forces that he had brought along with him.</hi> Not only ſo, but in his additional Declaration (we all may remember how occaſion'd) he moſt emphatically diſclaims, abhors, and renounceth all ſuſpicion of a <hi>wicked deſign of Conquering the Nation.</hi> And as jealous for the People, of their abandoning themſelves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, and their <hi>Deliverance</hi> too at laſt, after ſuch Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces given of their over-great and too eaſy
<hi>Paſſiveneſs,</hi> he yet further there minds them of the fatal Conſequences of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Free People of <hi>England</hi> under a Force, as that which would <hi>make void their own lawful Titles to their Honours, Eſtates,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97731:9"/> and Intereſts.</hi> This as it ſhews His
<hi>Majeſty</hi>'s great Wiſdom and Goodneſs together, ſo it ſerves to ſpeak and make appear the <hi>Conſiderateneſs and ſound Reaſons</hi> of the late Parliaments Proceedings in relation to <hi>the Army,</hi> and alſo ſtrongly implies the <hi>Defectiveneſs</hi> of what is yet done therein, which may not be unworthy your further Conſideration. For as it was one of the State-Policies, calculated to ſerve the ſiniſter Ends of the late Reigns, to neglect, diſcourage, and diſcountenance <hi>The Militia of the Kingdom,</hi> thereby to render it both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, and in a great meaſure uſeleſs, in order to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perinducing in proceſs of time, and as time ſhould ſerve, <hi>A Standing Force;</hi> ſo it appears but <hi>a reaſonable Jealouſy</hi> or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture, That notwithſtanding what is already done in this matter, if more do not follow, and that <hi>the Militia of the Kingdom</hi> at leaſt be not new-modell'd and better form'd, than it can poſſibly be on the Foot it now ſtands; it may yet prove, for want of ſome ready, diſciplin'd, domeſtick Power of one kind or another, to withſtand and oppoſe any Foreign At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; but as a
<hi>Poſtern-gate</hi> to let in at one time or other, <hi>A Standing Force</hi> upon the Nation; and then they that would have <hi>Honours, Eſtates, and Intereſts,</hi> (according to what goes before) muſt have them there or <hi>no where.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if Gentlemen, notwithſtanding <hi>our preſent ſure and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Peace,</hi> apprehend it requiſite <hi>as an immediate Guard and Defence of the Nation,</hi> to continue on foot for <hi>this one Year</hi> longer, a certain Number of Men (call them <hi>Regular Troops, a Standing Force or Army,</hi> or whatever elſe <hi>their Appellation</hi> be) yet taking the real meaning to be, <hi>That their Being ſhall deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine with the Year;</hi> it may nevertheleſs ſure with Decency and good reaſon be expected, not only that ſome <hi>ſpecial Reaſon</hi> be aſſigned, why Theſe muſt be continued <hi>This Year,</hi> more than <hi>The Enſuing;</hi> for a
<hi>Perpetual Reaſon</hi> and a <hi>Yearly Expedient</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond not over-well; and <hi>Perpetuity</hi> it ſelf is made up, and in ſome ſort conſiſts of <hi>One Year after Another.</hi> But further, I humbly preſume, it may moreover be expected, that <hi>the ſame Gentlemen</hi> will rather chuſe to move <hi>Firſt,</hi> than wait to <hi>Second</hi> any Motion for ſuitable Proviſions for <hi>Futurity;</hi> (ſuppoſe one be, for inſtance, as before, <hi>The new forming the Militia of the Kingdom;</hi> that thus, under the Cover of the foremention'd
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97731:9"/> 
               <hi>Expedient,</hi> this at leaſt may be gain'd, that it be better ſettled, Trained, and become more and every way uſeful; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon this ſuppoſition ſtill, that as yet we want what is ſufficient for <hi>the Safety, Honour and Happineſs of the Kingdom:</hi> The glorious Ends <hi>His Sacred Majeſty</hi> not only came hither for at firſt, but <hi>which is all</hi> (as he, to <hi>his immortal Honour</hi> be it ever ſpoken, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues gratiouſly to aſſure us in his late Speech to <hi>both Houſes of Parliament) he hath to ask:</hi> After which, I ſee not how it can any longer remain a doubt (if any hitherto hath been) but that <hi>an Engliſh Parliament</hi> will (and without <hi>prejudice</hi> to any their more particular <hi>Engagements</hi>) moſt carefully hold thoſe general
<hi>Engagements</hi> above-mentioned, to the <hi>Safety, Honour and Happineſs of the Kingdom,</hi> in all and every reſpect <hi>ſacred;</hi> or <hi>His Majeſty</hi> is but too like to fail of <hi>the honourable Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> he ſo graciouſly expreſſeth of <hi>the preſent Parliament,</hi> And they will appear to come infinitely below the thoughts he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd<note place="margin">P. of O's Letter to the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Army.</note> even of
<hi>the Officers of the late King</hi> James'<hi>s Army, who,</hi> he had goodneſs enough to <hi>hope, would not ſuffer themſelves to be abuſed by a falſe notion of Honour; but that they would in the firſt place conſider what they owed to Almighty God, to their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to their Country, to themſelves, and to their Poſterity, which they as men of honour</hi> (and it ſeems to hold much the ſame with <hi>all men of honour) ought to prefer to all private Conſiderations and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements whatſoever;</hi> but beſides the force and extent of theſe Conſiderations, yet even for the obtaining of the preſent ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Point in iſſue, <hi>a certain Land-Force for this one Year;</hi> As
<hi>ſuch proviſions and ſuch concurrence,</hi> (by removing all
<hi>Reaſonable Jealouſies,</hi> and by that means inducing Men of ſomewhat other thoughts, to quit their fears of this, or any preſent,
<hi>Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> that upon mature <hi>deliberation and debate</hi> ſhall be found <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally</hi> neceſſary) do both plainly and naturally tend to faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate the <hi>End;</hi> ſo they alſo help to make it eaſy
<hi>for the time,</hi> if not every way and altogether agreeable to thoſe of ſuch dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Sentiments; which, with humble ſubmiſſion I take it,<note place="margin">His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's late Gracious Speech to both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> is of <hi>more weight, and better account,</hi> than perhaps <hi>the bare car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying</hi> This, or, it may be, any Other Point can, in its ſelf, poſſibly be. It being beyond all contradiction no leſs than ſelf-evident, <hi>That the flouriſhing of Trade, the ſupporting of Credit, and the quiet of Peoples minds at home, will depend on the opinion they have of their Security.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97731:10"/>I have been the freer to give ſome before-hinted <hi>Jealouſies</hi> in this place the term of
<hi>Reaſonable;</hi> becauſe I obſerve, That <hi>the raiſing and keeping a ſtanding Army in time of Peace, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Parliament,</hi> is aſſign'd, in <hi>the Agreement of the Houſe of Lords, with the concurrence of the Houſe of Commons,</hi> as one of the Acts whereby the late King <hi>James did endeavour to ſubvert the Proteſtant Religion, and the Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom,</hi> and which (together with all other the particulars therein enumerated) was by them declared <hi>utterly and directly contrary to the known Laws and Freedom of this Realm;</hi> whereupon fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>the Abdication and Vacancy,</hi> which made way for, under God, our preſent <hi>Gracious Deliverer and Sovereign</hi> to fill the Throne, thereby to ſupply that <hi>Vacancy:</hi> And that theſe words, <hi>without Conſent of Parliament,</hi> ſtand part of this fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited Article, takes not off the force thereof: For beſides the foreignneſs of the Suppoſition, That <hi>a Free</hi> Engliſh <hi>Parliament</hi> would e're conſent <hi>to raiſe or keep up an Army in time of peace</hi> without ſome <hi>imminent danger apparently impendent on the Nation and Government;</hi> This only obviates the Exceptions and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence that might be taken from the <hi>Ways and Means</hi> of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by, or of retaining,
<hi>ſuch a Force,</hi> but by no means provides againſt the many and great Dangers (if no more immediate Evils) naturally accruing and ariſing
<hi>thence;</hi> which is by far the greateſt part of the difficulty, as it is moſt evidently <hi>of the laſt and utmoſt Concern to a free People:</hi> Now, how any can think it (if any do) altogether
<hi>unreaſonable</hi> to be, though but thus remotely, <hi>jealous for His Majeſty, and our own ſakes,</hi> of any thing that had ſuch a part in the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Fate, and the Nations Sufferings under him, is beſide, I confeſs, (or it may be rather, it ſurpaſſeth) my ſmall Capacity and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which way ſoever the merits of the matter turns, as to <hi>a Standing Land-Force, being a preſent neceſſary Expedient for preſerving the ſafety, honour and happineſs of the Kingdom:</hi> And as to what conſideration it may have <hi>Abroad,</hi> His Majeſty is alſo pleaſed in his before-mentioned late Speech, (ſo full of <hi>Wiſdom and Grace,</hi>) to give us this freſh Information and Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>That to preſerve to</hi> England <hi>the weight and influence it has at preſent on the Councels and Affairs Abroad, it will be requiſite</hi> Europe <hi>ſhould ſee, we will not be wanting to our ſelves.</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97731:10"/>But as to this, (and indeed in what not?) His Majeſty more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over had before acquitted himſelf in ſo ſolemnly declaring (§ 21.) the deſign of his Expedition to be, <hi>That ſo the Two Houſes may concur in the preparing of ſuch Laws, as they upon full and free debate ſhall judge neceſſary and convenient, both for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming and executing the Law concerning the Teſt, and ſuch other Laws as are neceſſary for the ſecurity and maintenance of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion; as likewiſe for making ſuch Laws as may eſtabliſh a good Agreement between the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and all Proteſtant Diſſenters; as alſo for the covering and ſecuring of all ſuch who will live peaceably under the Government, as becomes good Subjects, from all perſecution upon the account of their Religion, even Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not excepted; and for the doing all other things, which the Two Houſes of Parliament ſhall find neceſſary for the peace, honour and ſafety of the Nation, ſo that there may be no more danger of the Nation's falling at any time hereafter under Arbitrary Government;</hi> by which he fully refers to your Honours (as he ſtill continues to do); And there, in all humility, I leave theſe Conſiderations, at a Seaſon, which in many reſpects appears proper, and adap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſuch Cares and Endeavours: For an end being put to the growing Expences and Hazards of a tedious War, <hi>the time is come,</hi> that the Nation, by report at leaſt and ſpeech of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, has been
<hi>referr'd</hi> to: <hi>The Time is alſo come,</hi> that (ſuch as for diſtinction-ſake have been call'd) <hi>Whiggs</hi> are ſaid to be more in play, and have greater Parts and Intereſts in State-Affairs than formerly, who have hitherto loudly call'd for a full <hi>Regulation and better Settlement</hi> in theſe Matters: And God be thanked, our Caſe is not at preſent ſo forlorn, and paſt all remedy, that <hi>it ſhould ſeem to be with us</hi> (as Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> on another occaſion expreſs'd himſelf) <hi>as with decaying Merchants, almoſt become deſperate; who when Creditors call faſt upon them, being hopeleſs of paying all, grow careleſs of all, and pay none:</hi> And if <hi>Theſe</hi> neglect their Opportunities which <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> have, and do put into their hands (and more if they withſtand them) in ſo diſhonouring their own <hi>Principles,</hi> and ſinning ſo much againſt
<hi>knowledge and conviction,</hi> they'll en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the rendring themſelves
<hi>contemptible,</hi> and of becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more a <hi>common ſcorn,</hi> than I am willing to ſay; for thus, as <hi>Popiſh Policy</hi> ſowed Diviſions among us, that we might do
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97731:11"/> their work by, in our turns, devouring one another, when they, without our help, were not ſufficient to effect our Ruin; ſo <hi>Tories</hi> (as men have been diſtinguiſhed) might well laugh in their Sleeves, (nor ſcarce would they ſtop there) if the <hi>Whiggs,</hi> but through neglect or indiſcretion, ſuffer thoſe Evils to overtake
<hi>Poſterity</hi> which the Others could not (whether <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly or unwittingly</hi>) bring upon the preſent Generation; and ſo it would be juſtified beyond diſpute, that (though it would be hard perhaps, nay next to impoſſible it may be, to eſtabliſh the <hi>Government</hi> altogether by <hi>Tories,</hi> yet however that) it's alſo poſſible it may not be preſerv'd with <hi>Whiggs; Quod Deus avertat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were, 'tis confeſs'd, to a high degree vain to imagine, that ſo general a defection and corruption as well in <hi>Politicks</hi> as
<hi>Manners,</hi> as hath over-run the Nation ſince the very <hi>Remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable Reſtauration of King</hi> Charles <hi>the Second,</hi> ſhould be wiped off, corrected, and ſet right in an inſtant; but ſo your Faces, <hi>my Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> are but ſeen and obſerv'd to keep looking towards
<hi>the peace and proſperity of our Jeruſalem,</hi> that we continue not ſtill under <hi>a Government of Expedients,</hi> the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it's not to be doubted, will repoſe themſelves on you as their preſent beſt and ableſt <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> when to apply, and how to proportion either
<hi>Remedies or Preſervatives;</hi> and thus perſiſting, you'll ſtill more ennoble your ſelves, by giving more <hi>glory to God,</hi> in doing more
<hi>good to men;</hi> and beyond any thing beſides, thereby alſo will you endear His <hi>Sacred Majeſty (whom God long preſerve a publick Bleſſing to thoſe Nations)</hi> yet more and more to all His
<hi>Subjects</hi> univerſally, render His <hi>Reign happy,</hi> and His
<hi>Memory precious to all Poſterity;</hi> agreeable to the judicious Obſervation of a Wiſe and Experienc'd Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, now living, That <hi>a King of</hi> England <hi>at the head of His</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir <hi>W. Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> in his Eſſays.</note> 
               <hi>Parliament and People, and in their hearts and intereſts, can never fail of making what figure he pleaſes in the World, nor of being ſafe and eaſy at home; and may deſpiſe all the Deſigns of factious men, who can only make themſelves conſidered, by ſeeming to be in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Nation, when the Court ſeems to be out of it: But in run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on Councels contrary to the general humour and ſpirit of the People, the King indeed may make his Miniſters great Subjects, but they can never make Him a great Prince.</hi> Which, notwithſtanding
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97731:11"/> in its true and genuine ſenſe and ſignification, concludes not, but that at long run too, <hi>the King</hi>'s is as truly and properly His <hi>Miniſters Intereſt,</hi> as <hi>the People</hi>'s is always <hi>His.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to the Third and Laſt Error (or rather it may be Failure) that I ſhall at preſent mention, as affecting So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety in general, and which too is oft-times a conſequent of the preceding; and that is, The want of <hi>a Regular Exerciſe of good and wholſome Diſcipline in Church and State:</hi> For Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as hath been ever held) is <hi>the Life of the Law;</hi> and far better is it that Laws be not in many caſes made, than that they ſhould afterwards be <hi>neglected,</hi> and ſo fall into
<hi>contempt;</hi> for which reaſon 'tis a noted Rule, That
<hi>Penalties</hi> ought not to be too great, becauſe <hi>any over-great Penalty (beſides the Acer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity</hi>
               <note place="margin">L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                  <hi>Bacon's Reſuſcitat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>of it) deads the Execution of the Law.</hi> And
<hi>there is a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inconvenience</hi> (as) <hi>of Penal Laws obſolete and our of uſe,</hi> or in diſuſe, <hi>That it brings a Gangreen, Neglect, and Habit of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some, on behalf of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction,</hi> may poſſibly reply, That admitting the Error or Failure, it is not to be imputed ſo much to want of <hi>Good-Will and Intention,</hi> as of
<hi>Wealth, of Credit, and of Power;</hi> and that this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly may well be reckon'd one among the <hi>Deficiencies</hi> of our <hi>Reformation</hi> it ſelf; which neither will I altogether deny, but 'twould be more eaſily granted, if our <hi>Spiritual Guides and Governors</hi> were ſeen to exerciſe thoſe Powers they have, more ſtrictly to <hi>Edification,</hi> and in a more eſpecial manner over their <hi>own Body;</hi> ſo would they by thus <hi>firſt caſting out the beam out of their own eye,</hi> not only avoid the Reproach of <hi>Hypocriſy,</hi> but alſo <hi>ſee clearly to caſt out the mote out of their brother's eye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſay
<list>
                  <item>That they, who wait at the Altar, ſhould partake with the Altar,</item>
                  <item>That the Labourer is worthy of his hire,</item>
               </list>is not to ſay
<list>
                  <item>That they muſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, who wait not, or but little, there.</item>
                  <item>That he is worthy, who doth not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</item>
               </list> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:97731:12"/>To ſay
<list>
                  <item>That we may not muzzle the mouth of the Ox, that treadeth out the Corn,</item>
                  <item>That men ſhould eat of the Milk of the Flock, they ſeed,</item>
               </list>is not to ſay
<list>
                  <item>That the Ox which treadeth not, may not be muzzled.</item>
                  <item>That ſuch ſhould live of the Flock, as do not feed it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And ſuch like. No; ſo far from it, that it's a known
<hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im founded upon Natural Reaſon, That the Benefice is given for the</hi>
               <note place="margin">L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> B<hi rend="sup">p</hi> of Sarum's Paſt. Care.</note> 
               <hi>Office. But what ſhall we ſay, when we find often the pooreſt Clerks in the richeſt Livings? Whoſe Incumbents (not content to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vour the Patrimony of the Church, while they feed themſelves and not the Flock out of it) are ſo ſcandalouſly hard in their Allowance to their Curats, as if they intended equally to ſtarve both Curat and People.</hi> And yet the outcry of the <hi>Contempt of the Clergy,</hi> is upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion given out to proceed from the inſufficiency of their eſtabliſhed Maintenance. However, I find it queried, and that too by a Reverend Divine,
<q>Whether it be rational to proceed in this matter
<hi>Aſcendendo,</hi> to bring up the Lean Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariges to the Corpulency of Fat Parſonages; or <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo,</hi> to reduce the Gouty Benefices to the Medium of the Meagre Vicariges; and not rather, to make <hi>an Equality,</hi> that they may Both meet in the half way?</q> And when theſe <hi>Fat Kine</hi> ſhall have thus laid themſelves out to raiſe the <hi>Lean ones,</hi> a man without riſquing over much might poſſibly enſure, That the Laity, after this is done, ſhall readily and chearfully fill up and ſupply any then remaining <hi>Deficiency:</hi> For <hi>you'll</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Le Clere</hi> of Incredul.</note> 
               <hi>hear thoſe, for example, preach Charity and Impartiality, who have neither the one nor the other; but are wonderfully pleas'd to find thoſe they have to do with not ſelfiſh or uncharitable, becauſe it makes for their advantage.</hi> I have read beſides of, for a ſeaſon, a Painful <hi>Labourer in God's Vineyard,</hi> and who, being preferr'd by his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop for his Work ſake, to a much better (as 'tis call'd, <hi>i. e.</hi> a bigger) <hi>Benefice,</hi> fell off from the Exerciſe of his Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Function; and being ask'd how ſuch a Change was wrought? replied only, <hi>Parvae loquuntur Curae Ingentes ſtupent.</hi> To the ſame purpoſe Q <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was wont to ſay often upon the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97731:12"/> making a Biſhop, <hi>That ſhe loſt a good Preacher.</hi> And ſo the Woman in the Fable not content with one Egg a day, over fed her Hen, that ſhe laid none at all. And thus it may fall out with men now-a-days; for they who do not in a good degree employ the Faculties and Powers they have, would no more make due uſe, and improve greater, than people who neglect the preſent opportunities would retrieve the loſs of time paſt (was it to return again), tho ſcarce any thing is more common than to hear men ſpeak ſo; but their <hi>preſent Behaviour</hi> ſhews evidently, how apt we are herein to deceive <hi>our ſelves</hi> more than
<hi>others;</hi> ſo that it cannot be abſolutely ſaid, That 'tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<hi>the want of ſufficient Powers,</hi> &amp;c. as before, that is the cauſe no more is done towards the <hi>Reformation and Regulations</hi> neceſſary; nor that ſuch Powers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> alone can work thoſe effects, but as Men and Things are therewith alſo circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated.
<q>
                  <hi>In ſhort, Religion is a thing cannot be long kept</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reflection the Gr. of Deiſm.</note> 
                  <hi>up, as Secular Factions may be, by Intereſt or Grandeur, or any thing of that kind: No, it muſt have real internal eſteem in the hearts of men, otherwiſe the effect is very like to be, that they will leave that (i e.</hi> any ſeparate Mode or Eſtabliſhment) <hi>for ſome other, or elſe look upon all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to be only Trick and Deſign.</hi>
               </q> Theſe <hi>Prejudices</hi> lye ſo much and juſtly at the doors of many ſuch <hi>Complainants,</hi> that they are themſelves in a great meaſure to anſwer for the ill conſequences of this want of Powers (if ſo it be) which becauſe I do not wholly deny, but wiſh rather a <hi>Regulation</hi> firſt of thoſe in being, and then a <hi>Supply</hi> of what is <hi>defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> I will here obſerve another <hi>Prejudice</hi> which ſeems to have no leſs obſtructed the increaſe of theſe Powers, than the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and till remov'd will go nigh to continue an <hi>invincible Obſtacle</hi> to the enlarging them for the good, it may be, they might otherwiſe do, and which themſelves may charitably be ſuppos'd to intend; and this is, their ſo ſtrongly and ſo ſtrangely affecting <hi>a ſeparate and diſtinct Headſhip, Superiority, and Juriſdiction from, and over, the Laity;</hi> whereas the <hi>Powers</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> (except the immediate
<hi>Power of the Keys,</hi> which is purely indeed <hi>Spiritual</hi>) is wholly <hi>Civil,</hi> however at any time exerciſed by <hi>Spiritual perſons.</hi> The <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> 'tis true, hath been acknowledg'd to be <hi>Cuſtos utriuſqueTabulae;</hi> but I do
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97731:13"/> not underſtand that <hi>Prieſts</hi> are held to be, or are, ſo. And it's truly noted by a modern Writer, and well worth our Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
<q>That the tearing the Eccleſiaſtical Power from the<note place="margin">Eſſay of Magiſtr. Power. Poſtſc.</note> Temporal, was the curſed Root of Antichriſt; thoſe Powers were not diſtinct in
<hi>England,</hi> nor in moſt Nations, till the See of <hi>Rome</hi> got the Aſcendant; then, and not till then, did the Clergy attempt to bind the Laity by thoſe Laws they never conſented to. <hi>And in another place,</hi> That the Powers the Clergy claimed to themſelves, being inconſiſtent with the Principles of the Reformation, and, in <hi>England,</hi> with the Oath of Supremacy, and that Power the Laws have inveſted the King with, there is nothing ſo contradictory as their pretended Power, and that which they are forced to own does belong to the Magiſtrate: So that our High Churchmen are not conſiſtent with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, no, not in one point; but (what is worſe) aſſert ſuch Principles as make the <hi>Reformation</hi> it ſelf criminal; and which muſt unavoidably oblige a man that acts agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to thoſe Principles, to return to the <hi>Popiſh Yoke.</hi>
               </q> I find it likewiſe queried by the ſame Reverend Divine before referr'd to,
<q>Whether it be not more agreeable to the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Times, and the Nature of the Chriſtian Religion, that the Clergy ſhould have ſome dependance on the People as to Temporals, who depend ſo much on their Clergy as to Spirituals?</q>Who thereupon alſo notes,
<q> That we conſider the Inconveniences of a Depending Clergy, but not <hi>the greater ones of having them Abſolute and Independent.</hi>
               </q> No won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then if the <hi>Laity</hi> be, it may be, over and above jealous of intruſting more Powers with men of ſuch
<hi>Pretenſions;</hi> but remove the <hi>Obſtacles,</hi> and the
<hi>Effect</hi> follows, in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as naturally as the <hi>Cauſe</hi> being taken away, the <hi>Effect</hi> is ſaid and known to ceaſe.</p>
            <p>But then again as to the State, I am far from exciting
<hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour,</hi> or ſtirring up an <hi>extreme Execution of the Laws,</hi> as convinc'd that <hi>ſummum Jus eſt ſumma Injutia.</hi> And tho agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to what goes before, I hold that a due regard ſhould be had to a
<hi>Regular Exerciſe of Civil Diſcipline,</hi> yet I readily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs withal, that <hi>Example</hi> goes as much beyond <hi>Penal Laws and Human Penalties,</hi> as beyond <hi>Precepts;</hi> and therefore I deſire to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97731:13"/> be underſtood to lay the far greater ſtreſs there, according to what is ſaid at the beginning of this Paper; but yet <hi>the one may be done, without leaving the other undone.</hi> I will therefore conclude this Head, with an Inſtance aſſign'd as a Cauſe of the Deiſm of the Age, in ſome <hi>Reflections on an Account of the Growth thereof,</hi> in further Proof of the Force of <hi>Example,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond, as I ſaid, or <hi>Law or Precept;</hi> and which the Author ſeems at leaſt to allow as it were (<hi>propter duritiam cordis</hi>) as a Plea for the common practice he complains of and decries; and that is (in the Author's words) this;
<hi>That by the falſe Laws of Honour now in vogue, they ſee they cannot live and act like Gentlemen, and at the ſame time keep to the plain Rules of their Religion. Chriſt commands us to forgive Injuries, Not to render evil for evil: But if a Gentleman at preſent won't cut his Neighbour's Throat for a ſmall Affront, he muſt be contented to ſuffer himſelf, what is very hard to be born, to be expos'd, and counted a Coward, and be perhaps kick'd out of Company: By which means the Chriſtian Religion is really in a ſtate of Perſecution. Now this is a great ſnare to young Gentlemen, and muſt make very many of them reſolve rather to leave their Religion in that point, than undergo what is ſo hard to be born. And tho the Caſe do never happen to them, yet the very Reſolution muſt debauch the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, take away much, if not all the Authority Religion has over it, which muſt needs make that very uneaſy, and ſo incline him for his own quiet to throw it quite off, or come to deſpiſe it, as not being fit to be the Rule of the Life and Actions of a Gentleman.</hi> Which pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice notwithſtanding, however evil in it ſelf, and deſtructive in its Conſequences, is hardly, ſcarce poſſibly, to be ſuperſeded, till and unleſs the <hi>State</hi> ſo take upon it to inſpect, protect, and preſerve all particular mens
<hi>Reputations,</hi> and to judge and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine between them in thoſe nice and tender Points of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;</hi> ſo as by this means, or ſome other of the like or more efficacy, it become <hi>Reputable</hi> to appeal and ſubmit in ſuch matters to its final and peremptory <hi>Deciſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after all; the Buſineſs of a <hi>Religious and Civil Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> doth not wholy lye on any Set, or any ſort of men what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever (tho ſuch as ſit at the Helm of Church and State, ſhould no doubt lead, and may ſteer and influence a great way): But this is ſo much
<hi>every one's own</hi> in one kind and degree or another, as in his
<hi>reſpective Station</hi> to bear a part at leaſt (wherein, by the way,
<hi>the voluntary Societies of one and another Denomination now aſſociated</hi> for any of theſe purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97731:14"/> are particularly <hi>commendable,</hi> deſerve <hi>encouragement,</hi> and are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>imitation</hi>) in animating and encouraging our <hi>Heads and Chiefs,</hi> and in manifeſting in our ſelves, and helping to work in others, for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, a diſpoſition to ſo <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>ſuch generous Impreſſions,</hi> without which even the utmoſt care and endeavours, whether of <hi>preaching,</hi> or due <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing</hi> &amp;c. in our Superiors, will be <hi>labour in vain:</hi> For though mens <hi>Wills</hi> are often found very <hi>perverſe and obſtinate,</hi> yet there is nothing in Nature ſo ſtubborn and inflexible as <hi>the nature of things themſelves,</hi> which yet may be, and often is ſubdu'd, o'recome and corrected; but it's more by humouring it in ſome ſort<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> than oppoſing it; more by go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as it were, along with it, than againſt it: This His
<hi>Majeſty</hi> in His Princely Wiſdom hath admirably well conſidered in His late Royal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation <hi>for preventing and puniſhing Immorality and Prophaneneſs,</hi> (iſſued as <hi>thereunto moved by the pious Addreſs of the Commons in Parliament aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled;</hi>) as appears not only by his exciting in us a due ſenſe to whom we owe <hi>our peace,</hi> His ſo judiciouſly pointing at the unqueſtionable occaſions of the Nation's being ſo univerſally over-run with thoſe <hi>Enormities,</hi> His declaring <hi>His Royal Purpoſe and Reſolution to diſcountenance and puniſh all manner of Vice, Immorality, and Prophaneneſs, in all perſons, from the higheſt to the loweſt degree, within this His Realm; and particularly in ſuch who are employed near His Royal Perſon:</hi> But more eſpecially by His adding, <hi>That fer the greater Encouragement of Religion and Morality, He will upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions diſtinguiſh men of Piety and Virtue, by Marks of His Royal Favour.</hi>
               <q>For the Bulk of Mankind is ſo made, that there is no working on them, but<note place="margin">L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> B<hi rend="sup">p</hi> of <hi>Sarum</hi>'s Paſt. Care.</note> by moving their Affections, and commanding their Eſteem; </q> who yet with all their Natural Propenſions to Evil, are not ſuch utter Enemies to
<hi>Godlineſs,</hi> as to <hi>the Forms of it;</hi> nor ſuch Abhorrers of the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> as of the <hi>Craft:</hi> But would thus (without the myſtick Appendages of mens Inventions) be ſoon more thoroughly perſuaded, That</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Religion</hi> is neither the Effect of <hi>Chance;</hi> becauſe 'tis <hi>univerſal.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gent. Rel.</note> Nor of
<hi>Ignorance;</hi> becauſe it poſſeſſeth the moſt
<hi>Learned.</hi> Nor of <hi>State-policy;</hi> becauſe 'tis received among the moſt <hi>barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and unciviliz'd people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor of <hi>Frenzy or Madneſs</hi> (which ſometimes poſſeſſes men with very ſtrong Imaginations); becauſe there was ſuch a multitude of them who exactly agree in the ſame <hi>Sentiments;</hi> and alſo becauſe it appears both from the Writings and Actions of the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that they were men of <hi>Reaſon and ſobriety,</hi> and ſome of them perſons of great <hi>Learning,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But that there is a <hi>God,</hi> who has made all men, and has (as a Token of his Work) ſtamped and engraved this his <hi>Mark and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> upon them.</p> 
            </q>
            <p>Which is yet abundantly cleared and confirmed by the
<hi>Ineſtimable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations</hi> of himſelf ſuperadded to the Impreſſions, Light, and Law of Nature. In ſhort, if we, <hi>however dignified or diſtinguiſhed,</hi> did but ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſeek <hi>the praiſe of God more than the praiſe of men:</hi> were we found doing <hi>the Lord's work</hi> more than (what we too fondly call) <hi>our own.</hi> If we ſought <hi>Good,</hi> rather than a <hi>Great Living:</hi> In ſo asking, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely <hi>ſeeking firſt the Kingdom of God and his righteouſneſs, all theſe things would be added unto us;</hi> according as we find God dealt with <hi>Solomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97731:14"/>So would <hi>Religion</hi> no longer ſuffer under the opprobrious Nick-name of <hi>a Trade;</hi> but the <hi>Goſpel</hi> would run a-pace and be <hi>glorified,</hi> which wants nothing, but its
<hi>falſe Lights, Colours and Obſcurities</hi> to be done away, and its
<hi>Vails</hi> to be taken off, to ſpread far and near its <hi>true and native luſtre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Clergy</hi> would be renown'd beyond expreſſion; ſince <hi>Reverence</hi> and <hi>Eſteem</hi> is ſo inſeparably annexed to that <hi>high Calling and Office,</hi> that it may be ſaid of them, as our Saviour Chriſt ſaith of his own Life, <hi>No man taketh it from them, but they lay it down of themſelves;</hi> and <hi>in</hi>
               <note place="margin">John
10. 18. Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi>'s Paſt. Care.</note> 
               <hi>this we have good reaſon to reſt aſſured, ſince we do not find many Inſtances of Clergymen, who live and labour, who preach and viſit as they ought to do, that are under any eminent degrees of contempt;</hi> This ſhews evidently how pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous alſo and juſt is the Obſervation, That <hi>the moſt capital and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of all Abuſes is, That the falſe Opinion of the worſt Ages of Popery, that made the chief, if not the only obligation of Prieſts to be the performing Offices, and judged that if theſe were done, the chief part of their buſineſs was alſo done, by which the Paſtoral Care came to be in a great meaſure neglected, does continue ſtill to leven us; while men imagine that their whole work conſiſts in publick Functions, and ſo reckon, that if they either do theſe themſelves, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and hire another perſon in holy Orders to do them, that then they anſwer the Obligation that lies on them. And thus the Paſtoral Care, the Inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Exhorting, the Admoniſhing and Reſtoring, the Directing and Conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Viſiting and Comforting the People of the Pariſh, is generally neglected; while the Incumbent does not think fit to look after it; and the Curate thinks himſelf bound to nothing, but barely to perform Offices according to Agreement.</hi> And how natural and juſt is it, that ſuch, whoever they be, as in their own perſons neglect and contemn <hi>the great Duties of Religion,</hi> and of their <hi>proper Miniſterial Office,</hi> ſhould thence in concluſion draw <hi>contempt upon themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Church</hi> alſo would be united and eſtabliſhed upon <hi>a Rock,</hi> that not men, nor Devils, could prevail againſt, as (in the particular it relates to) is agreeable to the obſervation of its Right Reverend Dignitary, That<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>it was the Opinion many had of the Diſſenters ſtrictneſs, and of the looſeneſs that was among us, that gained them their credit, and made ſuch numbers fall off from us: They have in great meaſure loſt the good character they once had; if to that, we ſhould likewiſe loſe our bad one; if we were ſtricter in our Lives, more ſerious and conſtant in our Labours, and ſtudied more effectually to reform thoſe of our Communion, than to rail at their's; if we took occaſion to let them ſee, that we love them, that we wiſh them no harm, but good; then we might hope, by the bleſſing of God, to lay the Obligations to love and Peace, to Unity and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, before them with ſuch Advantages, that ſome of them might open their Eyes, and ſee at leaſt upon how ſlight grounds they have now ſo long kept up ſuch a Wrangling, and made ſuch a Rent in the Church, that both the power of Religion in general, and the ſtrength of the Proteſtant Religion, have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered extreamly by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> under God, <hi>our Great Deliverer,</hi> would be ſtill more and more eſteem'd and rever'd as a
<hi>Soverain-Benefactor,</hi> more than <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign;</hi> and ſo will
<hi>His Throne be eſtabliſhed by righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All <hi>State-Miniſters and Magiſtrates</hi> too, as
<hi>ruling well, would be counted</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aſhcam</hi> of Confuſ. and Revol of Gover.</note> 
               <hi>worthy of double honour,</hi> while they <hi>abandoning the dominion of their own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, take care of thouſands of others.</hi> So alſo will they in a great meaſure
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97731:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> avoid the <hi>Envy and Deſigns</hi> of many, who might otherwiſe aſpire to their <hi>Dignities and Offices;</hi> and in an eſpecial manner would they elude and divert, if not altogether prevent, the <hi>reproachful Malice of Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals</hi> of all ſorts and ſizes, who are ever forward to <hi>recriminate,</hi> and it may be, too too apt to hold themſelves <hi>excuſed,</hi> (by the Judgment they uſually, but corruptly, make from <hi>compariſon,</hi> not by the Rules of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Truth and Righteouſneſs</hi>) if they can but retort, <hi>Thou art inexcuſable.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 1.</note> 
               <hi>O man, whoſoever thou art, that judgeſt: For wherein thou judgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf; for thou that judgeſt, doeſt the ſame,</hi> or the like, <hi>things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, No more could <hi>the People</hi> hence fail of their particular Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, who would hereby find, that they enjoy the quiet, eaſy and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, as well <hi>fruits,</hi> as <hi>much better hopes,</hi> of their <hi>retirements,</hi> from ſuch <hi>perſons watching over them, and for them,</hi> that, as it were, encumber themſelves for their Service with</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That guilded Nothing, being Great;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mrs.</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips'<hi>s Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ems.</hi> Le Clerc <hi>of Incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhould all ſoon learn, and better underſtand, That (as)
<hi>we ſhould not court Honour, Riches,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but by lawful ways;</hi> (ſo) <hi>not as a means to live great, But to be uſeful to the Society wherein we live; and</hi> (that) <hi>this cannot be, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we are capable of duly diſcharging thoſe Offices which we ſeek, and of uſing thoſe Honours we are ambitious of, to good purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This would teach us to try, find out, and know our own
<hi>Strengths</hi> and <hi>Abilities,</hi> and thereby prevent, 'tis probable, much trouble both to our ſelves and others: For not every one, that, whether by feeling or ſeeing, finds a <hi>fault,</hi> is fit to be entruſted with its <hi>cure;</hi> 'tis not every <hi>Gooſe,</hi> that ſome how takes an
<hi>alarm,</hi> can ſave <hi>a Capitol;</hi> no, not even many, that are
<hi>maſters of reading,</hi> men of good <hi>Notions,</hi> and competent Judges of the <hi>Theory,</hi> are capable of the <hi>Practique;</hi> and that, among other Reaſons, for this material one, That, <hi>though they ſtudy Books, they read not, nor underſtand, Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it would be no ſuch hard matter to convince men, That all
<hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dane Goods, Pleaſures and Enjoyments whatſoever, are but permiſſive,</hi> in ſome ſenſe rather <hi>negative,</hi> than
<hi>poſitive,</hi> to be conſidered and accounted only as <hi>means,</hi> not as <hi>ends,</hi> and as ſuch, and no otherwiſe, are to be ſought after.</p>
            <p>This would inſtruct us how effectually (and that not without
<hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> and the trueſt <hi>Delights</hi> we are yet capable of) to moderate our <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> and ſubject our <hi>Ambitions,</hi> contenting our ſelves reſpectively with<note place="margin">Church-Catechiſ. Mr. <hi>Collier</hi> of the Stage.</note>
               <hi>doing our duties in that ſtate of life unto which it ſhall pleaſe God to call us;</hi> as knowing, that, <hi>in earneſt a Chriſtian's time for entertainment is not yet; that we are too craving and ill-manag'd, if we are ſo violent for delight—who</hi> (by theſe means, at leaſt, would better) <hi>know, Death ought to be our pleaſure; and therefore, tis hoped, Life may be a little without it: For as God makes Vertue the condition of Glory, and trains men up to happineſs by hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and Induſtry; ſo the Devil's Road to Deſtruction lies through Senſuality and Epicuriſm; and as pretended Evils lead us on to uncounterfeited Bliſs, ſo Viſionary Satisfactions are the cauſes of Real Miſery.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—Si quid noviſti rectius iſtis</l>
               <l>Candidus imperti; ſi non, his utere Mecum.</l>
               <bibl>Philalethes.</bibl> 
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
